the fence was also
бе забор тоже
building
строил
a bite And where is the heron far to go to the boat I
клёва А где цапля далеко идти до катера
understood I understood And where the heron has already flown away and has
понял понял А где цапля уже улетела в
flown away And there the boat I see everything now I see
улетела А вон катер всё вижу теперь вижу
the boat yes It’s such a small boat how can
катер да Это такой небольшой катер как
you catch 10 tons on it
ты на нём 10 тнн выловишь
No, well, it contains a maximum of 24
Не ну он максимум 24
Healthy ones I’m from  city ​​of
содержит Здоровеньки Я из города
Khmelnitsky Where are you from?
Хмельницкий Вы откуда
Tais is a beautiful flag. I saw it somewhere. Yes,
флаг Тайс красивый где-то его видел Да у
you also have a beautiful wall, but I haven’t seen one like that.
вас тоже стена красивая но я такой не
Where are you from from Kyrgyzstan,
видел Вы откуда сами из Кыргызстана
Kazakhstan? Oh, you guessed wrong. You’re
Казахстана откуда Ах не угадал Ты
Tajikistan, no, Uzbek, so Tajiks are
Таджикистан нет узбек так таджики же
Uzbeks, they don’t speak Russian well.
узбеки они по-русски говорить плохо
Well, maybe  just live now already
умеют Ну может просто живёте сейчас уже
settled in Russia Karakalpak no
обосновались в России каракалпак не
no Far East Ulchi region and you you
не Дальний Восток ульчский район а ты ты
this uh Ren Yes yes yes na No by
этот ээ Рен Да да да на Нет по
nationality who is Chukotka
национальности кто Чукотки
Ulchi what what is the name of your
ульчского как как как называется твоя
nationality
национальность
Ulchi I haven’t heard of that Ulchi
ульчского такое не слышал ульчи
Look there Google yes yes I’m
Посмотрите там загуглите да да Вот мне
interested in Ulchi  And the Ulchi yes Uh-huh Uh-huh
интересно ульчи А ульчи да Угу Угу Угу
It turns out, uh, you SZh with Manzhur were
Это получается э Вы СЖ с Манжура были
related one way or not
родственные так или нет
Which I don’t know, yes yes Tunguso mazhuzh
Какие не знаю я вот да да тунгусо мажуж
people Yes yes yes That is, it turns out that you are
народ Да да да То есть вы получается
autochthonous inhabitants of those
автохтонные жители тех
territories Cool, yes, but they write that there are
территорий Прикольно да но пишут что
about 3,000 Ulchi left according to the census
ульчи осталось порядка 3.000 по переписи
Yes, the last one seems to be two Well, like uh in
Да последней вроде бы две Ну типа ээ в
Russia
России
2472 2000 yes dadada 2500 2000 in short yes
2472 2000 да дадада 2500 2000 короче да
76 people in Ukraine even if it’s interesting
76 человек в Украине даже если интересно
yes Uh-huh and your language is still alive yes it
да Угу а язык язык ещё живой у вас да
turns out to be spoken Yes
получается разговорный Да
interestingly cool Type the word lucha
интересно прикольно Набери слово луча
lucha in English Yes
луча по уче ски Да
spiders wait  lucha in kulcha ski
паучки подожди луча по кульча ски
Uh-huh How can I
Угу Как тут
type lucha lucha ska No, well, in Google
набрать луча луча ска Не ну вот в Гугле
How to
Как
type Well, just type
набрать Ну так и набери
no no no so now that’s your self-name
нету нету так так сечас так самоназвание
Nani
у вас Нани
Yes na yes it’s called interesting yes no
Да на да называется интересно да нет
nasal nasal
насал насал
understood and since six years since 1926 they accepted
понял а с ше года с 1926 года приняли
the name of the official ulcha Cool Yes,
название официальной ульчи Прикольно Да
it’s interesting that they write that the religion is shamanism
интересно о пишут что религия шаманизм
animism you people don’t engage in
анимизм у вас люди е занимаются вот
these rituals like shamans Or
этими обрядами так шаманки Или уже
no longer yes Usually they call them Baptists or whatever
нет да Обычно называет баптистам или как
else it’s called Uh-huh interesting, of course
там ещё по-другому Угу интересно конечно
we do it Cool What, for example, did you
занимаемся Прикольно А чем например вы
live in these ulchis of yours  they lived along the
жили вот ваши эти ульчи жили вдоль
coast or on the mainland, that is,
берегов или на материковой части то есть
they were engaged in fishing like the
они занимались рыбными промыслами как
Aleuts, for example.
алеуты например
So I still live along the coast along
Так я до сих пор живу вдоль берега вдоль
the coast, I understood everything, that is, it turns out like this Coastal yes,
берега всё понял то есть это получается
well, but I can
такой Прибрежный да А хорошо а вот могу
show you, yes Well, let’s wonder if
показать да Ну давайте интересно
this is the coast
это берег
Yes yes I  I live here, I understand. But for example,
Да да я тут живу понял А например
it turns out that these Ulchis are yours, they
получается вот эти ульчи они ваши они в
mostly lived in some villages or towns like this
основном в сёлах посёлках каких-то жили
now, or they were scattered. Well,
так сейчас или разбросаны они были Ну
far from each other or lived compactly,
далеко друг от друга или компактно
yes, that’s what I asked so differently,
Да это что я спросил так по-разному
but who lived at sea
да кто на море
Yeah, who is good in the forests of the deaf? And
жил Угу Кто в лесах глухих хорошо А
look, where you live now, there are
смотри вот там где Вы сейчас проживаете
some other indigenous peoples,
ещё другие какие-то коренные народы есть
besides
кроме
you, there are
вас
Nanais in the
нанайца есть на
nai Yes, I thought there were nais in the north,
най Да я думал на най на севере
no, they are nearby near Khabarovsk
още Нет они рядышком возле Хабаровска
Nazca Yes, yes, Nanais, yes
находятся там Наска Да да да нанайцы да
these are the Nenets yes these are the Nenets in the north and the
а это ненцы да это ненцы на севере а
Nanais Yes the Nenets yes the Nenets yes the Nenets in the
нанайцы Да ненцы да ненцы да ненцы на
north Yes Ana Nati Yes too yes be silent
севере Да Ана Нати Да тоже да молчите
nay people of the Far East Yes
най народ Дальнего Востока Да
Cool you see what a difference there is
Прикольно видишь какой разница
Interesting eat there are Evens there are
есть Интересно есть есть эвены есть
Evenks food Evens and Venks I know this I
эвенки еда эвены и венки Я знаю это я
know the difference  Well, wait, you
знаю разницу Ну вот подожди ты
know incorrectly, the Evens, they
неправильно знаешь вот эвены они
came from the forest from the tree,
произошли от леса от дерева
so there are, uh, the Evenks are harmful, that and the
так есть э вредны есть эвенки та а
Evenks. From whom did they come, there are, there are
эвенки От кого произошли есть есть есть
aimki, so from Who did the Evens come from the
аимки так то От кого произошли эвены от
tree, the Evenks, from Who did they come from,
дерева эвенки От кого произошли
oh, it seems like from the air, I don’t remember  Honestly,
ой вроде бы от воздуха я не помню Честно
I’m not a race. So, who came from fire,
мне не рас Так а кто от огня произошёл
you came from the clan of bears, there are
учи произошли от род медведей есть
different clans, so that is, your people
разные роды так то есть ваш народ
came from bears, believe me, yes,
произошёл по поверим от медведей так да
from what
От каких
names Well from ours Well, there are different bears
имена Ну от наших Ну там разные медведи
you have, well, we only have one species
же у вас есть ну у нас только один вид
bears there are Boers or Yeah, I understand because
медведей там буры или Ага понял потому
there Maybe some Himalayan bears
что там Может какие-то гималайские
come to you, I don’t know, conditionally some
приходят к вам я не знаю условно
Chinese bears
китайские медведи
So by the way, that’s how long I’ve been living, I’ve
какие-то Так кстати вот сколько вот Живу
never eaten a bear, similar to
ни разу не ел медведя аналогично
Sokhatino, there’s elk there, well, there’s musk deer there, I’ve
сохатино вот лося там ну вот кабаргу там
eaten deer - musk deer -  What is this? Well,
изюбра ел кабарга - Это что такое Ну
like a goat, a goat got it,
типа козы коза понял
it’s cool, only a wild one
прикольно только дикая
got it. It’s so good, but now
понял Так хорошо а вот сейчас
it turns out. What do your Ulchis do? Fishing,
получается Чем занимаются ваши вот эти
hunting, hunting, and
ульчи рыбалкой охотой промыслом добычей
where do you give this result of hunting and
а куда вы даёте эту результат охоты и
fishing? Do you rent it out to some enterprises?
рыбалки сдаёте на какие-то предприятия
We sell
Барыга продаём Либо
hucksters. Or we treat them, so I have  I mean, this is some kind of
угощаем так я имею в виду это какое-то
enterprise or you caught something and
предприятие или вы что наловили то и
go, you provide for yourself or what?
идите вы сами себя обеспечиваете или что
Well, where do you go if you caught 10 tons of
Ну куда тебе если ты поймал себе 10 тонн
fish, where do you
рыбы куда тебе её
put it? So you catch them like poachers,
девать Так вы как браконьеры их ловите
or what don’t you understand? Oh, it happens in different ways,
или что не понял Ой по-разному бывает
I understand  Well, in short, no one is looking after
понял Ну там короче никто не смотрит за
this, so
этим те
maybe why is there a lot of climbing here? Well, what to
можно почему тут куча лазит ну а что
do with ten tons of fish? I just can’t
делать с деся тоннами рыбы Я просто не
imagine the freezing of salt, yes, it’s frozen well,
представляю морозь соли вяль да хорошо
you’ve salted it. In short, I gave you another 5
заморозил ты засолил Короче дал ещё 5
tons of salt; in short, there’s 10 tons of water, that’s all
тонн соли короче там 10 тонн вод всё что
you have with these  where you make tons of fish and then salt them
ты с этими де тоннами рыбы потом солёной
Well, I called on the phone,
делаешь Ну вот позвонил по телефону
the money arrived, they took
приехали деньги отдали забрали
the fish, and where are they
рыбу а куда они эти
taking these half-great somewhere to the cities? Yeah, I
пол пра где-то в города везут Ага понял
even realized that a couple of fish
даже до Москвы пару рыба
reach Moscow, some fish reach Moscow,
доходит какая-то рыба доходит до Москвы
all the way from you. That’s crap.  Whale whale crucian
аж так от вас Это ж капец Кит кита
carp pike there are all sorts of wait what crucian
караси щуки там всякие подожди какой
carp Kara pike is freshwater then
карась Кара щука - это пресноводная то
it’s your river Or the sea
это у тебя река Или море
there is a river And the river is Amur or whatever and the
там река А река это Амур или что там а
sea is nearby the sea is 90 km from me every
море рядом море от меня вот 90 км каждый
year e That’s all I thought that you were on the sea
год е Всё я я думал что ты на морском
I understand the coast
побережье понял
and what the name of the river is
а как река
Amur Amur Well, there’s a
называется Амур Амур А ну там а
settlement there. How interesting I am to see
поселение Как мне интересно посмотреть
how wide the Amur is there, you’ll see me
насколько там широкий Амур увидишь меня
on the map, probably
на карте наверное
something, that the village of Mongol Type the village of Mongol
что-что село Монгол Набери село Монгол
Uh-huh Khabarovsk Territory So there is yes Wow,
Угу Хабаровский край Так есть да Ого та
there the Amur in short oh there is spilling so
там Амур короче о там разливается так
that  there’s probably a bunch of them Yes, not these channels,
что там наверное куча Да не это протоки
well, it’s just Yes,
ну прото
not a bunch of them, but in short you won’t catch them all
Да не куча но Её короче всю ты её не
like Yes, yes, there’s probably
выловишь как Да да там наверное короче
such a fish there that can hit a pancake with its tail
такая рыба что может блин ударить
So of
хвостом Так что глаз
course you can knock out an eye Koluga and there are sisters,
выбить конечно Колуга а сестёр есть
yes it’s cool And what
да прикольно А чем
you catch with gear and nets is fun  sometimes
ловишь снастями сетями прикольно порой
with your hands or even with
руками а как
your hands Well, the Sokha fell off once you caught it with
руками Ну Соха она сорвалась раз её
your hands and threw it in. Or maybe you have
руками поймал закинул А может Вот у тебя
some kind of dried
есть какая-то вот дома сушеная самая
biggest fish at home, I’ve never seen a big fish,
большая рыба поть Я никогда большую рыбу
but no,
не видел а не не
no, can you show me what you’re
нету А можешь показать вот там чем ты
catching there with a boat?  or what have you Well,
ловишь там лодкой или что у тебя Ну
damn, what about going to the shore? Well, damn, it’s
блин что до берега идти Ну давай блин
interesting, it’s just
Интересно просто
crap Renault. I’ve never seen how the
капец Рено Я никогда не видел как ну
indigenous peoples really live.
реально живут вот коренные народы Вот
Look, you see the boat standing on the shore, I don’t see it, the
смотри видишь катер на берегу
heron is sitting, you see the ocher, I don’t
стоит не вижу он цапля сидит видишь охра
see the heron at all, I
вообще не вижу цапля
’ve got my shans on now.
достал сейчас шаны
everything is interesting to you BN look if
одену всё тебе интересно БН смотри если
I met some Russian I
бы я встретить какого-то русского мне не
wasn’t interested yes that’s a person yes from a
было интересно да вот так человек да из
small nation Well, I don’t rarely
малочисленного народа Ну я же не редко
meet
встречу
tacos Well yes, in principle there are only 2400
тако Ну да в принципе всего 2400
left so Lano Sigu I’ll take a
осталось так Лано Сигу возьму
blouse like this I need to wear it Yes it’s
так кофточку Надо одеть Да там
drizzling there  now I don’t know Well, it’s cold
моросит сейчас не знаю Ну холодно
it’s cold I
холодно
have scattered
имею разлетались
from the house there’s a heron I haven’t seen for sure
вот там из дома цаплю не видел точно
and up to
и до
the shore it’s interesting it’s interesting
берега интересно интересно
just
просто
yes wait Wait
да се подожди
Look what kind of bow he’s shooting from Wow
Вот смотри С какого лука стреляет Ого
bow Cool
лук Прикольно
let’s
да
go
пойдём
interesting interesting Well I’ve never
интересно интересного Ну я никогда не
seen Well since they live on these crafts Come on
видел Ну так как живут этими промыслами
let's
Давай давай
go get yourself a fence, built a
иди себе забор строил
bite And where is the heron far away go to the boat
клёва А где цапля далеко ити до катера
I understand Pony And where is the heron Ute in Ula And there's
понял Поня А где цапля Уте в Уле А вон
a boat I see everything now I see a boat and
катер всё вижу теперь вижу катер да
such a small boat as you can catch 10 tons on it
такой небольшой катер как ты на нём 10
No, well, it contains a maximum of 24 Listen, but
Не ну он максимум 24 содержит Слушай а
there  on the side it’s some kind of hill, it’s some kind of
вот там сбоку это какой-то холм это
mound or it’s just a mountain, not from any
Курган какой-то или это просто гора не с
other place, right there Yes, further along the coast
другого вот пря Да дальше по берегу вот
there,
там
not at the end of the coast, but it turns out there is a hill there
не в конце берега да получается там холм
like a mountain Yes, what kind of
такой гора Да что это за
mountain is this, it’s moss, I don’t mean a mountain, a
гора это мох не имею в виду гора гора
big mountain  Yes, what kind of
большая да вот это что за
mountain is this hill And show me And this is a volcano,
гора сопка А покажи А это вулканчик
like, it’s not just a hill, a hill And show me
типа не это просто сопка сопка А покажи
this moss,
этот мох
well,
ну
really, it’s not The grass is moss growing,
реально это не Трава это мох растёт да
yes Well, it’s not growing, it was brought by the current And
Ну он не растёт его принесло течением А
I understood it like algae, I understood it And you’re here
понял это как водоросли понял А ты тут
alone on this  do you live on the street or is there someone else there are
один на этой улице живёшь или ещё кто-то
a lot of people living, I just don’t
живёт куча людей просто людей не
see people Well, because they’re sleeping It’s still early How
вижу Ну потому что спят Рано ещё А
much do you have
сколько у тебя
now 5501 5501 Cool Yes, that’s
сейчас 5501 5501 Прикольно Да
interesting, [ __ ] it, now I’ll probably go, I’ll grab some
интересно капец да Сейчас поеду наверно
vodka, you’ll go by boat,
себе водки возьму
no, I’ll go by car, let’s go
катере нет на машине поеду давай поехали
for me  interesting to see Well, how are the
мне интересно посмотреть Ну как у вас
roads there?
там дороги
Shops
магазины
Lisa,
Лиза
come on, let's go, I'll tie the dog. Come on. Yeah,
давай давай поехали собаку привяжу Давай
interesting, the potatoes have already come out there,
интересно там картошка уже вылезла
Lisa,
Лиза
let's go now, the dog trailer, yes, let's
пойдём сечас собаку прицеп да да давай
not
чтобы не
run away. No, she doesn't just run away. It's a long way to the
убежала Да не она не убегает просто А
store. It's a long drive to the store,
далеко до магазина До магазина далеко
5 km.  Well, these are antlers and it works
ехать 5 км а ну это панты а он работает
in the morning
утром
No, not yet,
Да нет ещё
but how will you take it if it doesn’t
а как ты возьмёшь если он не
work, I’ll figure it out somehow Let’s be
работает как-нибудь разберусь Давай
interesting, damn I’m already
интересно блин аж
intrigued, I’ll go to the
заинтриговал поеду к
dealers, there’s
барыгам топлива
enough fuel to refuel soon, the car is
хватает заправляться скоро тачка
Japanese,
японская
anyway, make it so that I can see the
а сделай так чтобы я видел
road, phone number requests  you, of course Well,
дорогу телефон запросов у вас конечно Ну
damn it, I’m interested for this reason I’ve
блин так ради этого мне интересно Я
never seen the Cupid Well, it’s very
никогда не видел Амур Ну это очень
far from me, guess what, why aren’t you going
далеко от меня поди А что ты не едешь
already, the cruel river Yes, not now, I’ll go
уже река жестокая Да не сейчас это пойду
take the money But they’re
деньги возьму А
definitely lying there: the wife
точно лежали
is sleeping, there’s a wife, a
жина спит есть жена
son, yes, definitely, don’t Wake up the Son
сын да обязательно да не Разбуди Сына
only one son or do you have a grandfather? And
один сын только или ещё есть де да А
how old are you son and daughter and son and
тебе сколько лет сын и дочка а сын и
daughter
дочка
I was born in the ninety-first year myself
мне девяносто первого года рождения сам
I think it’s cool I’m eighty-first
считаю Прикольно я восемьдесят первого
and then you’re 10 years younger than me Wow Yeah
да то тебе на 10 лет младше меня Ух Ага
you’re 41 Gosh or 42 43 will already be a 43
тебе 41 Гош или 42 43 будет уже а 43 уже
you're already 33 No, no, you're a great guy, I know
тебе 33 Да не ну ты молодец зна ку Э ты
we're not going to pick up the car, we should have
что мы не едем за машиной то мы должны
gone Yes, not yet damn it Yes, I'm
были ехать Да пока нет ещё блин Да я
just waiting for my wife to wake up, I
только вот жду когда жена проснётся то
actually wanted to call the boys damn
вообще хотел позвонить пацанам блин
Oh wait, don't switch to the
Э подожди поди не Переключай на
boys
пацанов
Hello  I say, let’s agree, you
Алло говорю то давай мы договорились ты
’ll show me. Well, how is the road to the store?
покажешь Ну как это дорога к магазину
I was wondering how your nature is. How beautiful the
мне интересно было как у вас природа Как
nature is, damn it. Well, I’m already
дороги природа красивая блин тож Ну я
in the mood, you got into the car, I’m already
уже настроился ты сел в машину я уже
in the mood that we’re going,
настроился что мы едем
and how now I’m going to go wake up my wife, they’re not
и да как сейчас пойду жену будить не
sleeping.  Why, why should I
спят а зачем же А зачем жену
wake up my wife because I give her all the money?
будить потому что я ей все деньги отдаю
And I understand what the trick is, you went, I just did
А понял в чём фишка ты пошёл я просто
n’t find the money from my wife.
денег не нашёл деньги у жены
Now I understand why we’re not going to the store,
Всё теперь понял че не едем в магазин вс
but I think that you’ve gone, gone well. Well, that’s
А я думаю что ты пошл пошл хорошо Да ну
what money is.  gave for an apartment She
вот что денег дал на квартиру Она себе
bought herself an apartment well And for example And where did
купила квартиру хорошо А например А где
she buy an
она купила
apartment in Khabarovsk And what doesn’t live
квартиру в Хабаровске А что не живёт
in now will her son go there in the fall to study
в сейчас поедет осенью сына туда учиться
send to his son
отправлять сыну
how much sun do you need to know is
сколько тебе ВС надо знать это
to send to study is that he is no longer at
отправлять учиться это что он уже в
university
университет
He’s 7 years old and understood everything  listen, look,
нет Ему 7 лет всего понял слушай смотри
if, for example, there is no money so as not to wake up
если например денег нет чтобы не будить
your wife, well, at least just drive by,
жену Ну а хотя бы просто ну проедь
show me how the roads are like Damn, for the sake of it, I was just
покажи мне как дороги как Блин я ради я
waiting for me, it’s not a fact that you
аж прямо ждал мне ж не факт что ты
will buy something, I’m just wondering how
что-то купишь мне просто интересно как
it is, what kind of roads do you have, like yes  what kind of
это какие у вас дороги типа да какая
nature I saw I’ve never seen
природа вот я увидел Я никогда не видел
Cupid for me it’s really cool and I could I
Амур для меня это реально клёво и мог Я
never thought that she would be awesome Well,
никогда не думал что ей офигеешь Ну так
it’s necessary for the war to end Until O
это надо чтобы война закончилась Пока О
ends I can’t come So
не закончила Я не могу приехать Так
show me Let’s go for a ride
покажи давай Поехали прокатимся
Start the engine I’m here  and you’re there
Запускай двигатель как я ж тут а ты там
calling me Andriy By the way,
меня Андрий зву У тебя кстати
how do you hang out Uh-huh
как зависаешь Угу
[music]
[музыка]
everything is frozen
всё завис
Yes, we’ve
Да гаем
all arrived with a cap Damn, and I think that he didn’t
всё приехали Блин а я думаю что он не
go grandma didn’t find grandma, his wife takes him
поехал бабки не нашл бабки жена забирает
so that
чтоб
NN is in
нн в
slavery Yes, bachite people, tse VN don’t give a damn,
рабстве Да бачите народ це ВН не поха бо
you’re short  we didn’t donate to the channel in the
Вы короче на канал не донатили мы в
minuses the bulls in the pluses the bulo sent a
минусах були в плюсах було поихали
letter to my Telegram directly at the same time axis VN and
пись на мий Telegram прям зараз ось ВН а
Popik is more and more important YouTube
Попик це дуже и дуже важливо YouTube
took us through skarg orcs in your ban and
заня нас через скарг орки в твый бан и
even more videos I don’t show people sometimes I do
дуже багато вдео не показую людям вчасно
n’t show information about streams to that
не показуе информация про стримы тому
For this purpose, we need to write a Mali operational link
для того щоб ми Мали оперативный звязок
right away and while there in telegra
пишиться прямо зараз а пок там в телегра
okm video more tezh Tsikava and Korisna
окм вдео ще теж цикава и корисна
information and we are responsible for you trimati
информация и мы повинни з вами тримати
postiyny operational link will
постийний оперативный звязок
show you about Tsei
незалежно того покаже вам про Цей
YouTube Glory to Ukraine subscribe
YouTube Слава Украине подпишись